White House Tapes: Conversation 949-012, July 12, 1973
National Archives and Records Administration
Society of American Archivists
White House Tapes: Conversation 949-012
July 12, 1973
Nixon, Richard M. (President); Haig, Alexander M., Jr.; [Unknown person(s)]; Ziegler, Ronald L.; Tkach, Walter R. (Dr.)
597542 White House Tapes 17409633 Oval Office Sound Recordings 7450153 Audiotape 949
Richard Nixon Presidential Library and Museum
949-012
On July 12, 1973, President Richard M. Nixon, Alexander M. Haig, Jr., unknown person(s), Ronald L. Ziegler, and Dr. Walter R. Tkach met in the Oval Office of the White House at an unknown time between 5:09 pm and 8:22 pm. The Oval Office taping system captured this recording, which is known as Conversation 949-012 of the White House Tapes. Topics of conversation included President Nixon's health, public relations strategy, and Watergate, including the investigation by the Senate Select Committe on Presidential Campaign Activitiees (also known as the Ervin Committee), hearing testimony, and White House response.
This Oval Office recording is part of the Nixon Administration's White House Tapes, a secret taping program authorized by President Richard Nixon and active from 1971 to 1973.
July 12, 1973
July 12, 1973
certain
5:09 pm
8:22 pm
estimated
Recording Location and Taping System History
Beginning in 1971, President Richard Nixon authorized the installation of a secret taping system in selected portions of the White House, Cabinet Room, Oval Office, Old Executive Office Building, and Camp David. Collectively, these recordings constitute the Nixon Administration's White House Tapes.
In February 1971, the United State Secret Service installed listening devices in the White House. They placed seven microphones in the Oval Office: five in the President's desk and one on each side of the fireplace. The Secret Service technicians wired these devices to central mixers that were then connected to recorders in an old locker room in the White House basement. These recordings became known as the Oval Office recordings.
This system was a secret taping system maintained by the Secret Service. Only President Nixon, H. R. Haldeman, and a few of the President's close personal assistants knew the system existed. One of its key features was that the recording equipment in the Oval Office, the EOB office, at Camp David, and on the telephones was sound-activated, operating without a conscious decision by the President to record a specific conversation. The taping system was tied to the Presidential Locator System, which was also operated by the Secret Service, and was designed to continue recording for fifteen to thirty seconds after the President left the room.
On July 16, 1973, Special Assistant to the President Alexander Butterfield revealed the existence of the White House taping system during his testimony before the Senate Watergate Committee. Following this public revelation, White House Chief of Staff Alexander Haig ordered the removal of the entire presidential taping system.
Collection Overview
Conversation Summary
On July 12, 1973, President Richard M. Nixon, Alexander M. Haig, Jr., unknown person(s), Ronald L. Ziegler, and Dr. Walter R. Tkach met in the Oval Office of the White House at an unknown time between 5:09 pm and 8:22 pm. The Oval Office taping system captured this recording, which is known as Conversation 949-012 of the White House Tapes.
Topics of conversation included President Nixon's health, public relations strategy, and Watergate, including the investigation by the Senate Select Committe on Presidential Campaign Activitiees (also known as the Ervin Committee), hearing testimony, and White House response.
Audio Quality
The audio quality of the Nixon White House Tapes is generally poor. While some locations generated better quality recordings than others, inferior recording equipment, cheap tape stock, improper microphone placement, taping system malfunctions, volume fluctuation, background noise, and electrical interference contributed to the poor quality of the recordings. Other noises greatly affect the audibility of conversations, including such small happenings as the signing of documents or the clinking of coffee cups.
As a result of the microphone coverage, Oval Office conversations have clear audio relative to other Nixon White House Tapes. Even still, extraneous room noises and background sounds are evident and can obscure portions of conversations. The microphones in the desk picked up the sound of anyone writing on the desk or the setting down a coffee cup or a glass. Furthermore, the desk microphones captured the sound of President Nixon's chair banging into the desk, the President's feet banging on the desk as he put his feet up, and the sound of the President's knees knocking against the kneewell of his desk. The microphone installed near the telephone captured the ringing of the telephone, which sometimes blocked out small portions of conversation. On occasion, the helicopter rotor blades from Marine One completely obliterated conversation taking place in the Oval Office. The recording system also captured the sirens of ambulances, fire engines, and police vehicles as they blared in through open windows. On occasion, the opening and closing of interior and exterior doors briefly interfered with conversations.
Nature of the Recording
The White House Tapes comprise secretly recorded human conversation. Most participants were unaware that their meetings and telephone calls were being recorded. The taping system captured often unstructured and free-flowing discussions between close personal associates intimately familiar with the topic. As a result, users may find the recorded conversations difficult to follow.
Collection Arrangement
About the Subject Log
To assist listeners in understanding the conversation and finding segments pertinent to their own interests, a team of archivists has created a Subject Log, which outlines major topics, names, and organizations in sequential order.
Logs include action statements, which indicate when someone entered or exited a room. Action statements are underlined.
If a conversation recorded in one of the offices also captures a telephone conversation, a cross-reference to the corresponding telephone recording is provided.
If a telephone recording also captures a conversation taking place in one of the offices, a cross-reference to the corresponding room conversation is provided.
Logs indicate which portions, if any, were reviewed under the 2007 Deed of Gift.
In some cases, the Watergate Special Prosecution Force or court-ordered mandates resulted in a transcript of the entire conversation or portions of conversation. For these portions, archivists have provided a citation to the related transcript.
Audio Format
This conversation was recorded to audiotape on a system maintained by the United States Secret Service. The National Archives transferred the original audiotape to Digital Audio Tape (DAT), which, in turn, was later converted to digital audio files.
The audio recording of this conversation has been digitized and made available to the public.
The White House Tapes are currently undergoing preservation remastering, from which digital derivatives will be made and released to the public as appopriate.
Determination Categories
These processing categories are governed by the Presidential Recordings and Materials Preservation Act of 1974 (PRMPA); and the 2007 Deed of Gift. These categories are based upon the constitutional and statutory duties of the President of the United States, as well as the Watergate investigation.
Location of Recording
Oval Office, White House, Washington, D.C.
Related Topics
United States. President (1969-1974: Nixon); Audiotapes; United States -- Politics and government -- 1969-1974; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; Presidents -- United States
Topics of Conversation
People
Haig, Alexander M., Jr.; Nixon, Richard M. (President); Tkach, Walter R. (Dr.); Ziegler, Ronald L.; [Unknown person(s)]
Organizations
United States. Congress. Senate. Select Committee on Presidential Campaign Activities
Topics
Public relations; Watergate Affair, 1972-1974
Digitized Audio
The original audio has been converted to digital format and is available to the public as an MP3 file.
The original audio has been converted to digital format and is available to the public as a Broadcast WAVE Format (BWF) file.
Conversation Subject Log
- The President met with Alexander M. Haig, Jr.
  - Deed of Gift Segment
    Released per 2007 Deed of Gift
    - [Withdrawn Item No. 1], withdrawal-949-012-w001; 00:00:17 (Timecode ##:##:## - ##:##:##)
      Restricted as Personal-Returnable Material
    - President's schedule
      - President's health
        - Medical test
  - President's schedule
    - Walter Reed Army Medical Hospital
      - Meetings
    - Statement on national economy
      - Paper
  - Watergate
    - Access to files
      - Senators' possible response
        - Carl T. Curtis
          - William E. Timmons
            - Creativity
          - Barry M. Goldwater, Sr.
      - White House response
        - Decisions on Vietnam War
          - Cambodia, December 1972 bombing
        - Ervin Committee's possible demand
          - House Un-American Activities Committee [HUAC]'s 1953 subpeona to Harry S. Truman
      - White House staff response
        - Melvin R. Laird
        - Bryce N. Harlow
      - Samuel Dash
      - Possible White House selection
    - Richard A. Moore
      - Ervin Committee statement
        - John W. Dean, III
        - President's knowledge
      - Previous attack by Dean
      - Meeting with Dean regarding President's knowledge
      - Rose Mary Woods
    - Dean
      - Conversation with President
        - White House staff involvement
        - Full disclosure
        - Dean's possible testimony
    - Access to files
      - J. Fred Buzhardt, Jr.'s search for precedents
      - Archibald Cox
        - Possible removal
    - Ronald L. Ziegler's press briefing
      - President's contacts with Samuel J. Ervin, Jr.
        - Letter, telephone conversation
    - President's conversation with Ervin
      - Ervin's reaction
    - White House response
      - Elliot L. Richardson
      - Goldwater
        - Access to President
        - Harlow
        - Ziegler
    - Edward J. Gurney's possible meeting with Laird
    - Ziegler's press briefing
      - President's forthcoming meeting with Ervin
      - Ziegler's schedule
- An unknown man entered at an unknown time after 5:09 pm.
  - Request for Ziegler
- The unknown man left at an unknown time before 5:23 pm.
  - President's health
    - Track record during Presidency
    - President's schedule
      - Announcement
      - Forthcoming economic package of Phase IV controls
        - Walter Reed Hospital visit
        - Radio address
      - State Dinner
        - Zulfikar Ali Bhutto
          - Spiro T. Agnew
      - Visitors to hospital
- Ziegler entered at 5:23 pm.
  - Watergate
    - President's conversation with Ervin
      - Leaks
        - Newspaper column
    - White House response
      - Ervin Committee leaks
        - Florida
    - Goldwater's statements
    - George H. W. Bush
      - Conversation with Harlow
      - Possible travel
    - President's conversation with Ervin
      - President's schedule
        - Wire service coverage
        - Ervin Committee staff
        - Howard H. Baker, Jr.
        - Ervin
          - Possible subpeona of President
          - Access to files
    - Access to files
      - President's July 6, 1973 statement
        - Perception of compromise
    - President's schedule
      - Ervin
        - News leads
    - Moore
      - Ervin Committee testimony
        - Statement
        - Cross-examination by Terry F. Lenzner
        - International Telephone and Telegraph [ITT]
          - Mitchell
        - Ervin's comment to Dash
    - President's conversation with Ervin
      - Ervin Committee's goal
    - Leonard Garment
      - Meeting with unknown group, July 12, 1973
    - President's schedule
      - Ervin
        - Timing
          - Press coverage
        - Location
      - Baker
        - President's conversation with Timmons
    - Access to files
      - Cox
        - Buzhardt's views
          - Constitutional issue
        - Haig's view
          - Possible removal
      - Possible selective release
        - Laird, Harlow, Goldwater
        - Gerald L. Warren's press briefing
      - Story, July 12, 1973
        - Rowland Evans, Robert D. Novak
        - Gurney
        - White House staff reaction
          - Laird, Harlow
      - Dean, Mitchell, Moore
      - Possible allegations against President
      - Possible selective release
      - Possible allegations
      - Dash
    - Dean
      - September 15, 1972 meeting with President and H. R. ("Bob") Haldeman
    - Ervin
      - Treatment of witnesses
        - Mitchell
      - Conversation with President
      - Michael Gravel
      - Ervin Committee
        - Relations with White House
      - Garment
  - Deed of Gift Segment
    - President's schedule
      - President's health
        - X-ray
        - Viral pneumonia
    - [Withdrawn Item No. 3], withdrawal-949-012-w003; 00:00:42 (Timecode ##:##:## - ##:##:##)
    - President's health
      - Electrocardiogram
      - Publicity
      - X-ray
      - Naval clinic
      - Publicity
        - Leaks
      - Announcement
        - Viral pneumonia
      - Public relations [PR]
- An unknown man entered at an unknown time after 5:23 pm.
  - Request for Dr. Walter R. Tkach
- The unknown man left at an unknown time before 5:44 pm.
  - President's health
    - Announcement
      - X-ray
        - Results
        - Privacy
      - Prognosis
      - Potential Bethesda Naval Hospital visit
      - Privacy of X-ray visit
- Tkach entered at 5:44 pm.
  - President's schedule
    - Naval Medical Clinic visit
      - Timing
      - Security, visibility
  - Deed of Gift Segment
    - President's health
      - Diagnosis
      - Examination, X-ray
        - Extent of condition
    - [Withdrawn Item No. 4A], withdrawal-949-012-w004a; 00:00:32 (Timecode ##:##:## - ##:##:##)
    - Public relations [PR]
      - President's health
        - Possible hospital visit
          - Diagnosis
          - Walter Reed Army Medical Hospital compared to Bethesda Naval Medical Center
          - Timing
          - Announcement
            - Projection of heart attack, stroke
            - Press reaction
            - Perception of national calamity
            - Compared to other presidents
              - Stroke, diabetes [?], heart attack
              - Lyndon B. Johnson
        - Announcement
          - Tkach
            - Content
            - Statement
        - Prognosis
          - Symptoms
          - Camp David compared to hospital, White House
            - Weather
        - Announcement
          - Wording
            - Symptoms
            - Viral pneumonia
            - Diagnosis
              - Lung damage
            - Influenza
            - Virus
            - Fever
          - President's location while sick
    - [Withdrawn Item No. 4B], withdrawal-949-012-w004b; 00:00:24 (Timecode ##:##:## - ##:##:##)
    - President's health
      - General wellbeing
      - Possible hospital visit
        - Attendants
          - Military personnel [?]
          - Manolo Sanchez
        - Immediate departure
        - Need for diagnosis
        - Announcement
          - Symptoms
          - Undetermined diagnosis
            - Escalation of rumors
            - Need for private X-ray at naval clinic
      - PR
        - Hospital visits due to viruses
        - Diagnosis
          - Appearance of tiredness
          - Hospital visit
  - Presidency
    - President's opponents' goals
    - Press relations
      - President's obituary
- The President left at 5:59 pm.
  - PR
    - Announcement regarding President's health
      - Hospital
      - Tkach [?]
      - President's recent appearance
        - Tired eyes [?]
      - Honesty
      - Credibility
      - Timing of President's illness
      - Tkach's night visit and diagnosis
- The tape cut off at an unknown time before 8:22 pm.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Portions of this conversation are closed to the public:
Four (4) withdrawals, restricted as Personal Returnable Material
Access is governed by the Presidential Recordings and Materials Preservation Act of 1974 (PRMPA); Nixon Public Access Regulations 36 CFR 1275 of the NARA Code of Federal Regulations, including the 1996 Tapes Settlement Agreement (Appendix A); and protocols related to classified national security information, including Executive Order 13526.
For more information, please contact the Tapes Team at the Richard Nixon Presidential Library and Museum: nixon@nara.gov or (301) 837-3290.
Acquisitions Information
Presidential Recordings and Materials Preservation Act of 1974
The Nixon-era White House Tapes are subject to the Presidential Recordings and Materials Preservation Act of 1974 (PRMPA). PRMPA, which applies only to the Nixon Presidential Materials, stipulates that those materials relevant to the understanding of Abuse of Governmental Power and Watergate are to be processed and released to the public prior to the release of all other materials. Materials related to the Abuse of Governmental Power and the constitutional and statutory duties of the President and his White House staff are retained by the National Archives. PRMPA mandated the promulgation of access restrictions for the processing of the Nixon Tapes.
The resulting Nixon Public Acccess Regulations 36 CFR 1275 state that the National Archives must segregate and return to the estate of former President Nixon those materials identified as purely "personal-private" or "personal-political," and unrelated to the President's constitutional and statutory duties. This conversation has been processed under these regulations.
2007 Deed of Gift
However, in 2007, the estate of Richard Nixon negotiated a Deed of Gift with the Richard Nixon Presidential Library and Museum. By this agreement, materials deemed "personal-political" have been deeded back to the National Archives for release to the public. Materials originally deemed "person-private" have been deeded back to the National Archives, with the exception of materials concerning the medical history or non-Watergate-related personal finances of Richard Nixon or the non-public activities of the First Family.
This conversation has been re-reviewed under the provisions of the 2007 Deed of Gift between the estate of Richard Nixon and the National Archives. Changes in access have been noted.
Description, encoding, and public access to the White House Tapes subject logs are supported by a partnership between the Richard Nixon Presidential Library and Museum and the Office of Innovation at the National Archives and Records Administration.
Digitization of the White House Tapes and related activities by the Richard Nixon Presidential Library and Museum are supported by the Preservation Programs Division and the Office of Innovation at the National Archives and Records Administration.
Encoded by Amanda T. Ross, January 15, 2016
Edited by Amanda T. Ross, June 21, 2016